Can you all hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Yes, we can hear.
Let's wait a few seconds. Okay.
I can start just add spectacles.
Okay, we're going to continue our series
of lectures on training neural networks.
So, here is what we've learned so far.
Neural networks are universal
approximators,
but we must train them to approximate
any given function and they are trained
to minimize a total error on a training
set. This is essentially an instance of
empirical risk minimization and we use
variance of gradient descent to perform
this minimization. The gradients are
computed using back propagation.
We also saw that vanilla gradient
descent may be too slow or unstable. So
better convergence can be obtained
through uh second order methods that I
didn't present in class but they were on
the slides. These normalize the
variation across dimens dimensions.
We can use adaptive or decaying learning
rates to improve convergence.
Methods like R prop that decouple the
dimensions can improve convergence. And
momentum methods which emphasize
directions of steady improvement and
deemphasize unstable directions can
provide better convergence. So we'll
pick up from here. We're going to talk
today about So, does everybody remember
these topics? The ones that we just
mentioned. Were there any questions
about those topics?
See one thumbs up. Maybe I can see 20
and then I can move on.
So, give me some thumbs up if we're good
so far.
All right. I assume you're good so far.
So we're going to continue today with
incremental updates and we are going to
revisit trend algorithms. In the next
class we'll talk a bit about
generalization and tricks of the trade.
So let's start with incremental updates.
In the standard training formalism we
had a function we wanted to estimate but
we didn't actually have the entire
function. What we had was a set of
training in instances consisting of
input output pairs at a number of
locations and we use these to estimate
the entire function. So the way we did
it we defined uh a loss which was
basically the error at all of these
instances.
We start with an initial function,
basically an initial setting of your
network parameters, and then compute how
changing the network parameters a little
bit affects the error at each of these
locations. And we might find that we
want to increase the function at these
two places where the current function
underestimates the target. That we want
to decrease the function at these two
locations where it overestimates it. and
maybe increase the function at this
location. So the derivatives will give
us this information and subsequently we
adjust the function to in the correct
direction. So it maybe increases the
function in these locations, decreases
it a little bit over here, increases it
over here, and then we evaluate the the
error and the derivatives again. And we
find that the function still needs to be
moved up at these locations,
down at these locations, and up again at
these locations. So that's what we do.
And we keep repeating this until
uh we get arbitrarily close to the
target function at the training points.
Now, can somebody
suggest something that might not quite
be
uh nice about this procedure?
Some potential problems with this
procedure. Anybody overfitting?
Anything else in terms of compute?
long, expensive, high compute. How can
you tell me how how how it is high
compute? Repeated divergence.
We have to we have to process the entire
training data because we are trying to
adjust the network
uh parameters. We were trying to adjust
the network to correct the error over
all of the training instances.
We must process all the training data
points before making a single
adjustment.
So this is what we call a batch update.
In order to perform a single update of
the function, every single training
training instance must be processed
forward pass backward pass and then we
compute the average derivative over all
of them. And that's how you adjust the
function. So that can be very expensive.
And so here is our first problem.
Okay, 10 seconds.
Five.
See no more responses. So
uh
can anybody anybody tell me which of
these statements are true?
All of them right? All of them are
right. The actual loss function we try
to estimate minimize requires batch
updates. Batch updates minimize the
total loss over the entire training
data. So they actually to optimize the
actual loss function but then they
require processing the entire training
data before we perform a single update.
So patch updates are a bit like this guy
who has many hands and who's trying to
shape a lump of clay into a target, in
this case a doll. And so you' be
adjusting the clay at every single
location all at once. But anybody who
has done any modeling with putty knows
that you don't actually suddenly sprout
20 hands and begin to adjust the adjust
the clay. You do it with just one hand.
And what do you do? You poke it at one
place. You keep adjusting the clay one
place at a time. But then when you do
this,
there's there's a small challenge over
here. You can just compress the entire
thing all at once. Here when you poke
the clay at one point, it tends to pop
out in another place. And so you have to
account for it. So in this latter case,
what would be different about the adjust
adjustments you make compared to the
first case?
What would be the difference in the
second case?
Anyone?
Anybody?
Few mistakes.
So the thing is over here because you're
compressing the claim all locations all
at once. You can push the whole thing
all at once and take big steps. over
here the adjustments you make must be
small because if you make too large
adjustments then a poke at one place can
make the thing pop out in a completely
different place in a bad way. So the so
each poke is going to result in a
smaller change of the shape than in the
first case. Anybody who's done any kind
of modeling with clay knows that you
want to do this very carefully.
You agree with that?
Yes or no?
Right? And so that's basically the
principle that we're going to take over
here. We're going to adjust the
function, but instead of trying to
correct it everywhere all at once, we
will correct it one training point at a
time. So maybe we take this randomly
choose this training point and then find
the derivative and push up the function
over here. things that happen at other
locations too as a result of moving it
up here. So to make sure that bad things
happen in other don't happen in other
locations, we'll keep this adjustment
small. Then you pick up some other
training instance and then adjust the
function to reduce the error there and
then yet another training instance and
then adjust the function to reduce the
error there. And we keep doing this and
at each time we will keep the
adjustments small. Yet eventually when
you processed all the training data
points, you would have adjusted the
entire function and you would
potentially have done so with greater
overall adjustment than if you had made
a single batch update. To see how that
works, well, here's a pseudo code for
uh how this is implemented. You'll be
given training data points and as you go
through all the training data points for
each training data data point you may
you immediately make an adjustment to
the weights.
So the iterations can make multiple
passes over the data
and a single pass through the entire
training data is what we call an epoch.
An epoch with a training set with t
samples results in t updates of
parameters. So Bruno to answer your
question this actually will make many
more corrections to the function than if
you perform a batch update for the same
compute.
So here is the overall incremental
update pseudo code. Again in each pass
a pass is called an epoch. You go
through all the data and after each data
instance you make an adjustment to your
parameters.
There are some caveats in order for this
to work.
So to illustrate this consider this
example where I have eight training data
points four on this side four on this
side and the kind of function I'm trying
to res to learn is restricted to being
somewhat parabolic. So as I go through
the training data, I might just find
initially that when I process these four
training data points, all of them are
asking me to push the function down on
the left hand side. So I do so and then
the function pops up on the right. Then
I move to the right and I make
adjustments for the function on the
right. What would happen if I make
corrections on the right hand side? What
would happen
over here? anyone?
This would be pushed down and
this thing is going to go up, right? And
so I just keep looping back and forth. I
can get cyclic behavior
because when I correct it on the left,
the right pops up. When I correct it on
the right, the left pops up. How can I
fix for this?
How can I fix for this? Any suggestions?
Randomize, clip it. You want to select
your data in random order. So you must
go through them randomly to get more
convergent behavior. Maybe pick up one
data point over here, adjust the
function here a little bit, not very
much, right? Then you go over here. The
next time instead of going through these
four, if you pick something random,
maybe you pick up a function over here,
and then you make an adjustment over
here. So if you keep random randomizing
the order or in which you pick the
samples then you will not get the cyclic
behavior and you can expect it to
converge. This is one requirement. And
so when I think of this in pseudo code
in terms of pseudo code within each
epoch, how do I achieve this
randomization of our samples? It's very
easily done. I can just randomly permute
all of my training data within each
epoch. Which means the order in which I
go over the data changes from epoch to
epoch. Is this making sense to
everybody?
this one this bit.
Right.
So the story so far in any gradient
descent optimization problem presenting
training data instances incrementally
can be more effective than presenting
them all at once provided the training
data instances are presented in random
order. This is what is called stochastic
gradient descent. It's gradient descent
because we're performing gradient
descent. It's stochastic because the
training data instances are being
presented in random order. This process
is not specific to neural networks.
Stoastic gradient descent is a generic
algorithm that can be used for
optimizing any uh optimization in any
empirical risk minimization problem. We
also apply to train neural networks.
So why does this process of incremental
updates work and under what conditions?
For why? First consider a very
simplistic explanation that's often
given. Let's look at an extreme example.
Now remember you have no control over
your trading data. So let's consider the
extreme case where
uh all the training data point are
exactly the same. know how does the
gradient itself behave? The gradient is
the derivative of the overall loss which
is simply the average of the derivatives
of the divergences for the individual
training instances
and the
gradients for the individual training
instances will all point in different
directions because each individual
training instance needs a somewhat
different correction of the parameters.
So the overall correction shown by the
pink line over here is going to be an
average of all of these guys. So that's
why although all of these guys point in
different directions, the net correction
is going to be like so. But now if all
of your training data points were
exactly the same, this is what I call
data clotting. all the data have clumped
together and so in this case all of them
happen to fall at the same location.
Now if I compute the average derivative
over all the training data points will
that be any different than the
derivative for a single data point? What
do you think?
No. Right? And so in this case when I
compute the derivative of the loss with
with respect to the network parameters
since all of these guys are identical
every one of them is the same. So this
average is the same as the derivative
for a single instance. So although I
have a whole bunch of training data
instances, when I've done when I'm done
computing all of those, I'm going to get
exactly the same gradient as I would if
I just looked at one guy. And so here is
what would happen. If I were performing
a batch update, I'd process all of them
and take the average derivative and then
make an adjustment according to the
average. And what would happen after
having processed three t training data
instances, all I've succeeded in doing
is making one small adjustment to the
overall function. Whereas when I'm
performing stochastic gradient descent,
I'm going to be making an adjustment
after every single one of those training
instances. So although the individual
adjustments might be smaller together
the t corrections can end up being much
greater than the one single correction I
make on this side. So stochastic
gradient descent gets t updates for the
same computation as you would have if
you were performing batch updates. That
make sense?
Yes or no? Right. So
now to answer Bruno's question, are we
actually going to see data of this kind?
Likely not. But what if my data are not
all identical, just very similar? Would
the same principle hold? What do you
think?
Would the same principle hold? That if I
made a correction after every training
instance, I'm going to get an net
overall improvement.
What do you guys think?
Right. So Bruno, what do you think? That
was your question. Right
now when as the training data get begin
to get more and more diverse, when will
the benefits from stoastic gradient dis
eventually vanish? What do you think?
When would it vanish?
Anybody?
Come on. This has got to be easy, right?
So, if they're all identical, obviously
it's a win. If they're very similar,
it's a win. So, when when would these
benefits vanish? What do you think?
Somebody answer?
When it's diverse enough, when the
training data are random, right? When
they're very dissimilar. So, as the data
get increasingly diverse, the benefits
of incre incremental updates decrease.
They don't entirely vanish, but they do
decrease. So, did this make sense? All
of this this explanation of why you can
expect stoastic gradient descent to be
more effective than batch batch
training.
Yes or no?
Okay.
Well, that's not all there. There are
more considerations, right? So, what are
the additional considerations and
exactly how well does it work? Now to
for this first term for the additional
considerations I'm going to uh use an
example a very simple example of a
linear regression through origin. So
this is not any arbitrary neural
network. This is a linear regression
through origin. It's used purely for
purely for the purpose of illustration.
But whatever I say here is going to hold
for any complex function including
neural networks. So let's say I'm trying
to find a line that goes through the
origin such that the total projection
error on this line is minimized. This is
basically finding a regression line
through these data points.
One way to find it, of course, is to do
a global optimization. And when you do,
you're going to find a very simple a
very simple formula to get this line.
That will be easy. But then if I begin
to do it incrementally,
when I present just one training data
point, where will the line go? Say like
this guy, where will the line go? I'm
helping you with the figure.
So if I have gave you just one training
data point, where would the line go?
Prove the point, right? And then I'm
done with this data point. I pick up
another data point.
So when I give it a new data point,
where will the new line go when it's
adjusted?
Where will it go?
Average
through the latest point and the origin,
right? Because you're always minimizing
the latest error. You're grade you're
when you're performing stochastic
gradient descent, the error being
considered is only the error of the
latest sample. And so when you correct
for the error of the latest sample, it's
going to do something like this, right?
Yes or no?
Will it ever converge?
So how can you help me?
How can you help me with this one?
Any
suggestions? Momentum
average
smaller updates. Okay, Jenny, can you
explain more?
>> Um, so I was thinking that maybe instead
of jumping to a point, uh, we adjust the
line so that it moves towards the point
slightly.
So what you would want to do is that as
you go through the data data points the
model always updates the uh minimizes
the error on the latest instance but the
learning rate can be shrunk with
iterations.
So initially it just goes through the
data point. The next time you don't
swing all the way to the data point but
fall short of it. The next time
you're always swinging a fraction of the
way. So it's using an even smaller
fraction. And so if you keep doing this,
eventually the learning rate is going to
become so small that the line doesn't
change anymore. And at that point, it's
going to be fixed. And hopefully it's
going to give you the correct answer.
Does that make sense?
Yes. No. Right. I'd like to see some
thumbs ups to to to ensure this made
sense.
Okay. Okay, I see eight. Make that 20
and I'll move on. All right, perfect.
Right. So, incremental learning the
uh R prop and momentum are still batch
methods. We are looking at the entire
training and training data. But we will
talk about momentum later in this
lecture and their and its relevance to
incremental learning. But those are more
about how we adjusting individual
parameters on their own. Here we are
speaking of the influence of having just
one training instance at a time. That
one training instance is going to
correct all of your parameters and it's
going to drag it towards itself. So the
amount by which you let it drag it
towards itself must keep decreasing over
the training instances over the
iterations. Did that answer your
question Sean? Right. Okay. So
incremental learning you update the
model to always minimize the error on
the latest instance.
And so the caveat is we must shrink the
learning rate with iterations for
convergence. And so eventually the
correction for the individual instances
with the eventual minuscule learning
rates will not modify the function. At
that point you would have converged.
This is what the pseudo code now looks
like. These are the epochs. Within the
epoch you first randomly permute the
data. This is this is critical otherwise
you'll get cyclic behavior. Then within
each epoch over each training instance,
the learning rate itself is going to
shrink as you go over the iterations
over the training instances slowly until
eventually these corrections are too
small to really make a difference.
So this make a sense this make sense to
everybody?
Yes. Huh?
Okay.
How slowly
can must the learning rate shrink?
There are rules to this. You can't just
shrink the learning rate arbitrarily.
There's always uh this has to be
controlled. And to see how this must be
controlled, ignore the text for now. Um
yes the cosign uneing scheduleuler will
also have a shrinking learning rate
always have a shrinking learning rate
and to see why that is the case let me
consider this example right let's say
this is your initial
estimate this is say w0
and
let's say this
is your optimum this W star. So you want
the iterations to go all the way from
here to here. What is the worst case
distance between W0 and W star? What is
the worst case distance?
How far away can you be in the worst
case? Infinity. Right? So this distance
could be
infinity.
Now let's say the derivative dl / dw
is bounded meaning dl / dw is always
lesser than or equal to some upper bound
u. Okay,
because your loss function doesn't have
infinite slope. So the derivative is
always bounded, right?
And let's say the learning rate at the
kth iteration is a k.
So the total correction within any step.
So the kth
correction
is going to be
lesser than or equal to a k
time u.
Is this making sense?
because the derivative is upper bounded
by U and this is the learning rate. So
is this making sense?
Yes or no?
I see one yes. What about the rest of
you guys? Can I see a few more yeses?
Thumbs ups. 20 of them, right?
So
what is the total correction I would
make over the entire training? The total
correction I would make over the entire
training is going to be summation. K
equals
1 to infinity
k
and d l over d omega dw at the k
iteration. This is the total correction,
right?
Yes. Now
what's the upper bound on this?
What is the upper bound on this?
What is the upper bound someone?
This is going to be less than or equal
to summation a k
time
u. Is this is this making sense?
Yes. Now,
okay. But then how far are we going to
have to travel in the worst case? How
far are we going to have to travel in
the worst case?
Anyone?
What's the worst case distance to cover?
Infinity. So this
must be infinity
to guarantee convergence, right?
Yes or no?
Which gives us our first
condition. The summation of the learning
rates must be infinite.
This make sense to everybody?
Yes indeed, Bruno, you're right. Okay,
so uh now but then the learning rates
must shrink, right? So how do you say
that the learning rates if the learning
rates are summing to infinity that looks
like maybe they're not shrinking but
then we want them to shrink. So the
second condition that says that comes in
is that the sum of the squares of the
learning rates must be finite. This
ensures this ensures that you can always
get to the solution
always you can not that you will but
this ensures that you can always find
war star and this ensures shrinking.
So are these making sense these two
conditions?
Yes or no? Okay. And can you tell me a
learning rate scheduleuler that
satisfies both criteria?
Someone
can you tell me a learning rate
scheduleuler that satisfies both
criteria?
Momentum. No, no, no. I'm asking of what
what can a k be a k is a series, right?
That changes with k. What kind of series
is sums to infinity but is not?
Geometric doesn't necessarily always sum
to infinity, right? 1 / n. What is
summation n= n= 1 to infinity?
1 / n. This is what is this?
What is this guys? This is the harmonic.
And what does it sum to? A infinity,
right?
But what about n 1 / n^2
is this? Does this also sum to infinity
finite right?
This converges right
exactly. So someone asked me how is this
possible? We actually have it turns out
that there are other such se sequences
but the fastest converging series that
satisfies both above requirements as a k
is proportional to 1 / k.
So more learning uh general learning
generally our learning rates are
huristically determined we tend to have
things like these
but if you look at the hull the hull
probably goes as 1 / k. So to ensure
that both these properties are
satisfied. So this is the slide making
sense everything over here making sense
so far
right and so the loss is convex SGD
converges to the optimal solution
guaranteed for non-convex loss losses it
will still converge to a local minimum
so any questions so far
yes no
okay so here's
So cosine analing it decreases. So the
the point is that uh you don't this is
the hull
you want a hull that goes off like this
within this hull anything that does that
is also fine
then answer a question expert. So you
can also have things like this
as you answer your question. Okay,
so
here's a very nice example. This I
pulled this off the web. This was not
for training a neural network. It was
for training K means. And uh this is the
number of training CPU cycles and the
total error. They ran this multiple
times. So this bar shows you the the v
the standard deviation across multiple
runs. This is with batch gradient
descent. And you can see with batch
gradient descent it converges almost to
zero and the variance across different
runs is very small. With SGD it
converges much faster.
But what do you observe? It converges
faster. But what are the issues over
here guys? What are the issues?
What do we observe?
Anyone?
high variance and the error is much
higher, right? So it swings a lot and it
doesn't get quite close to even where
you are in the very first iteration of K
means. And so we have a problem.
Let's
but before that here's your second home.
10 seconds, guys.
Let me start this.
Okay.
By online, what is meant by online is a
process that keeps making its
corrections as the data come in. So, is
the first statement true or false? Okay.
Which are the true statements here?
Anyone? Which are the true statements?
First one's true. Second one,
true or false? True. Third,
all of them are true, right?
So SGD is an online version of batch
updates. It can have oscilly behavior if
we do not randomize the order of inputs.
It can converge faster than batch
updates but it can arrive at poorer
optimum. Convergence to the global optim
minimum can only be guaranteed if step
size is shrink across iterations but sum
to infinity in the limit. So so far so
good. Now let's try to understand a
little more for why we have this kind of
variance etc. Right? And for that, let's
go back and look at the objective
function we actually wanted to minimize.
What was the function we actually wanted
to minimize? That was this guy, right?
The integral of the divergence across
the entire training data. It is the
because you're also including the
probability. It's the expected
divergence across the entire training
space, across the entire input space.
Everybody remember that this was what we
actually wanted to minimize.
Yes. No.
Okay. So, we want to minimize the
expected divergence. But are we actually
minimizing this guy or are we minimizing
something else?
What are we doing?
Are we actually minimizing this or are
we minimizing something else?
It's approximation. And what kind of
approximation was that?
It was
the average, right? G of X is not known.
So what we are minimizing is the average
divergence across all training data
points and we are hoping that somehow
this works out. But then there's a very
nice uh uh property over here. If I take
the expectation statistical expectation
on both sides. If I take the expectation
of the loss, this is going to be the
expectation of 1 / n
summation divergence across the training
data points which is going to be 1 / n
summation of
this n summation of the expectation of
the divergences.
Right? And so I have the expectation of
the divergence is is the same if I for
all my training data points if I treat
them as random variables. So it's 1 / n
* n * the expected value of the
divergence
and the these two cancel out. So what we
find is that the expected value of the
empirical risk is actually the expected
divergence. I'm assuming the math made
sense to most of you but you didn't get
the intuition. Is that correct? What
exact
that the math is obvious but you don't
understand what this is saying. Would
that be a good judgment for all of you
guys?
Okay. So what this means is that if I
say let's say I decide to take a
thousand training data points and I run
many many experiments. In the first
experiment I choose some random thousand
data points. I find the loss. In another
experiment, I choose another random set
of thousand points. So in each
experiment, the training data are
different. So in each experiment, the
loss is going to be different. But if
you take the average of the loss over
all of those experiments, that average
is in fact going to be this guy, which
is the expected divergence. That's what
the math tells us. Which is why we use
our loss as an approximation to the
expected divergence because on stat as a
statistical expectation this is
justified. So we say the empirical risk
is an unbiased estimate of the expected
divergence because in expectation it is
the correct thing. But that's a
statistical statement. it. In practice,
there is no guarantee that minimizing
this will minimize the expected
divergence. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes.
Yes, Bruno. Because the average is over
a bunch of given training data points,
right? Expectation is a statistical
expectation over the entire space.
The expectation is the average remember
is is the area of the uh is the shaded
area. The average is some simply the
average over the samples. The difference
make a is that difference clear Bruno?
Okay. So now this is one. But there's a
second statement. Suppose I have xhat
equals x1
+ x2 and so on. Right? All the way to
xn. Each of them is an independent
random variable. Then what is the
variance of X1? How does the variance of
or how how does the variance of X hat
relate to the variance of these guys?
Anyone?
What is the variance of a sum of
independent random variables?
Anyone?
Can you tell me?
Be quicker, guys. I'll run out of time.
So, what is the variance of a sum of n
independent random variables?
anybody
sum of variances right this is going to
be summation i
variance of
x i
suppose I take 1 / n
over here
then what happens
1 / n is a scaling factor Right? So
variance is the second point. This is
going to be 1 / n²
summation of the variances. What if all
of the random variables have the same
distribution?
Then what happens? If all of the random
variables have the same distribution,
what happens here?
It's simply going to be 1 / n variance,
right? varian of x because you're
summing n of them and one one and n each
will cancel. So that clear to everybody
this one here? Yes. No.
Okay.
And so Bruno because you're multiplying
by 1 / n, right? It's 1 / n * something.
But the variance is the expected value
of x - mean squared, right?
So that means this 1 / n gets squared.
That answer you
answer everyone. Yes. Okay. So
won't a random sample have to be with
respect to the underlying? Yeah, it's
assuming that it's with respect to the
underlying distribution. So the point is
this. The variance of the empirical risk
over here is simply 1 / n the variance
of the divergence at any individual
points. So the variance is proportional
to 1 / n. This is what we just showed.
So the larger this variance, the greater
the likelihood that the the the w that
minimizes the empirical risk will differ
significantly from the w that expects
the that minimizes the expected
divergence. So the larger the variance
of this guy,
the more likely you are that the
minimizer of the loss is not going to be
the minimizer of this guy. That make
sense to everybody?
Yes. Now?
Yes. Okay. All right. I'm assuming
that one person who said yes represents
all of you and I'll continue on. Right.
Did that make sense? Okay.
So
now SGD at each iteration SGD focuses on
the divergence of a single sample.
Right? So the divergence of a expected
value of the divergence of a single
sample is still the expectation of the
divergence. So it turns out that even in
SGD although you're focusing on only one
sample, the sample divergence is an
unbiased estimate of the uh expected
error because you're just taking an
expectation, right? The uh formula
didn't depend on how many samples you
are averaging. But the variance it's
proportional to 1 / n. And in this case
in SGD the variance you have only one
sample. So n is one right? And so this
is n times the variance of the empirical
average that is minimized by the batch
update which is why the uh variance that
we saw was much greater for SGD. That
make sense?
Yes. Now
well even if it didn't I have some
pictures. Right. So here the blue curve
is the curve function that we're trying
to estimate. The red curve is the
current estimate of the network. And
what we want to find is the W that
minimizes the shaded area. But we don't
have the entire area. Instead, we have a
bunch of training data points. And we
are minimizing the average error over
all of these training data points. So
what happens if I use this current set
of training data points? It's going to
there are 1 2 3 4 5 six of them. It's
going to tell me that the function must
be increased here, here, and here. And
it must be decreased at these three
locations. But if I had a different
bunch of six data points, because
remember your training data points are
randomly chosen, right? And if I got
these six, then this is going to tell me
that the function must be pushed up
everywhere. On the other hand, if I got
these as my training data points, it's
going to tell me that the function must
be pushed up pushed down in the entire
middle region and pushed up at the
boundaries. So although I'm I have six
training data points in each case, the
prescription from the training data
points is entirely different in each
case. That is what we mean by the
variance that depending on the set of
training data points the uh the uh what
is suggested by them can change wildly.
That make sense?
Yes. No.
Right. So how do you fix this?
How what is one way to fix it?
Anyone? What's one way to fix it?
Here's the answer. Right. many many more
training data points. If I have lots of
training data points, then the chance
that they're together, they're going to
give you very different prescriptions
between when you change the training set
becomes smaller because just by having a
larger number of training data points,
I'm much more likely to cover the entire
space properly. This make sense?
Which is why the variance is inversely
proportional to the number of training
data points.
Right. Okay. Is everybody good with
this? Because I'll move on from here.
Yes or no? Give me some thumbs up. I'd
like to see some 20 thumbs ups.
Seven.
All right. So now here's what happens
with SGD. I have only one training data
point at each step. So that training
data point might fall here. It's going
to say, "Oh, the function's perfect.
There's nothing to do." A different one
might fall here and you it might tell
you please push the function up
everywhere. Yet another training data
point might fall here and it's might
it's going to tell you please push the
function down everywhere. Right? So
because depending on the location of the
training data point the prescription can
be wildly different. you're going to get
a huge variance with SGD. Which is why
when you look at the variance for SGD,
it's so much greater than the variance.
That's right, Sean. Than the variance
with full batch.
That make sense to everybody? Yes. No.
Why this is so much wilder?
Right.
Okay. So can you suggest something?
Suggest a fix. The reason we wanted SGD
is that we didn't want to process the
entire training data before each update.
But on the other hand, it gives us this
wild swing. So can you suggest something
that's
maybe
uh
take a subset of the data many batch
right? SGD uses the gradient from only
one sample at a time. So it's high
variance but also provides significantly
quicker updates than batch. Is there a
good medium?
Here's what I will do. Instead of taking
one data point, I'm going to take a
small number of subset of data points
and say adjust the function at a small
randomly chosen subset of parts keeping
the adjustment small at each time just
like you would in SGD. So maybe in the
first step you randomly chose these
three guys. You made an adjustment for
these three. the next time around you
chose these three guys. You made an
adjustment for these three, right? And
so if you keep choosing random subsets
of data points at each uh at each step,
you're going you're somewhere between
full batch which is too expensive and
SGD which is too noisy where so long as
the this is what we call a mini batch.
So long as the mini batch is diverse
enough, you can hope to get the the
appropriate correction over the entire
function. So this makes sense to
everybody.
Yes. Now,
right? And so here is the pseudo code
except that within same as before except
that within each epoch, you're going to
process many batches of data. So you
have a mini batch size, you still have
the shrinking step size and all the rest
of it is still relevant because you're
not processing the entire training data.
So what's the math behind this? The math
behind this is very simple. As before,
the expected mini batch loss is the same
as the expected divergence. So the mini
batch loss is also an unbiased
estimator. But then if you look at the
variance of the loss, that variance is
now proportional to 1 / B where B is the
mini bat size. So if I take a plot where
this is the mini bat size B and this is
the variance of the loss and this starts
at one. So this guy is going to be the
variance of the divergence itself
and then somewhere out here is going to
be 1 / n times the variance of the
divergence. This is the full training
this this is the full training data.
It's the full batch. So the variance of
the loss is going to fall off as 1 / b
which we all know has a curve of this
kind right
does is does everybody understand this
curve this is the mini bat size this is
the variance of the loss right and so
this here is the best loss that you can
get the best variance that you can get
for from your training data and so
so long as the variance of the mini
batch is close enough to this guy, that
mini batch is going to give you
something that's very similar to the
full batch itself.
That make sense?
And for
that size as small as 1,000 at you can
still get a variance of 10 raised to -3.
Right?
So we use many batch we don't use SGD.
Right? That's what I'm saying. With mini
batch with SGD, this would be the
variance. With full batch, this would be
the variance. With a mini batch of size
B, as the B increases, this is how the
variance falls off. You can choose a
point somewhere here, and you're still
going to get a pretty small variance
across your answer. Does that answer
your question, Duna?
Okay. And so, here's where we are,
right? The mini batch loss is also an
unbiased estimate of the expected loss.
The variance of the mini batch loss is 1
/ B * the variance of the divergence.
This will be much smaller than the
variance of the sample error for SGD.
And so here is the same experiment as
before. This was SGD. This was full
batch. This is mini batch. And what you
observe is that it converges to almost
as low an error as the full batch
with just a slightly greater variance
but as quickly as SGD.
This makes sense to everybody.
Yes or no?
So,
I'd like to see some more thumbs ups
before I move on.
Okay, I'm capped at 11, guys. I was
hoping for 20, but I'll move on. Right.
So again, convergence is generally
defined in terms of the overall training
loss, not sample or batch loss. But you
will never compute the overall training
loss because you're not going to process
your entire training data in each mini
batch. So we generally plot estimates or
the loss on the latest mini batch when
you actually uh draw your plots in all
of your abilation experiments or you
would maintain a running average of the
loss of a mini batches. Simply figuring
out how to plot your loss itself is an
art.
So in practice
uh training is usually performed using
mini batches. The mini batch size is
generally set to the largest that your
hardware will support in memory without
compute compromising overall compute
time because larger mini batches mean
less variance. Larger mini batches also
result in fewer updates per epoch. So
there's a bit of a tension here. The
convergence depends on the learning
rate. The simple technique you fix the
learning rate until the error plateaus.
Then reduce the learning rate by a fixed
factor like 10, right? And you still get
this hull which follows roughly uh the 1
/n trend. But then you have advanced
methods, adaptive updates where the
learning rate itself is determined as
part of the estimation. And that is our
next and final topic for today.
Bruno. Yes,
but you have never ever going to be in
that situation. We work with trillions
of data instances these days.
Okay, 10. Good. 10 seconds, guys.
Okay, let me stop this.
And can somebody give me the answers?
Which ones are true?
Which are the true statements here?
Anybody?
Which are the true 1, three, and four?
1 3 and four. Right? Because when in the
batch size is one, mini batch descent is
exactly the same as SGD.
So these three are
uh
Some of you can't see the polls. It has
to do with zoom. So the story so far SGD
you present training data instances one
at a time. This can be more effective
than full batch training provided
they're presented in random order. For
SG to SGD to converge the learning rate
must shrink sufficiently rapidly with
iterations. Otherwise the learning will
continuously chase the latest sample.
SGD estimates have higher variance than
batch estimates. Many batch updates
operate on batches of instances at a
time. So estimates have lower variance
than SGD and convergence rate is
theoretically worse than SGD. But
because you can perform batch processing
on GPUs and such like overall it ends up
being much more effective. Right? So
what is for saying mini batch gradient
approaches batch updates and variance
but SGD in efficiency. It's basically
saying exactly what we saw in this plot.
Right? In performance it's approaching
patch updates but in variance but in
efficiency it's per approaching SGD. Uh
did that answer you?
Yes.
I'm assuming it did. Okay. So
now let's revisit trend algorithms.
We said something about uh momentum
methods. What did we say? We said that
if the gradient keeps changing direction
randomly then you want to sort of uh you
know these were your gradients then you
want to maintain the great derivatives
in the direction of constant
uh motion and you want to sort of reduce
the the effect of the of the gradients
of the derivatives when they keep
flipping. And so we did this by
maintaining a running average. You
remember this?
Yes. Now
okay. So why was the gradient changing
randomly from instance to instance? The
gradients can change randomly due to two
reasons. One is of course the loss
function. When I plot the loss function,
the gradient at each location is
different. Right? The gradient here is
going to be so like so but the gradient
here is going to be like so. So as you
keep moving across the loss surface, the
gradient is going to change. Another
reason for the gradient to keep changing
is if the loss function itself changes
from iteration to iteration. Can you
remind tell me of an instance where that
happens? Where the loss function changes
from iteration to iteration?
Where does it happen guys?
Anyone?
Large learning rate. No, no, that has
that's a learning rate, right? When does
the loss function change from iteration
to iteration?
Online training, right? SGD, mini batch,
you're using a different set of training
instances in each iteration. As a
result, the loss function, which is the
average of the divergences on the
current set of training instance
instances also changes from iteration to
iteration. And this can result even if
you're standing in one spot, this can
result in a complete completely
different gradients in each iteration.
That make sense?
Yes. No.
Right. And so in this case
we really need to sort of worry about
these trends and such like a lot more
than you do in batch descent because you
have added an extra reason for the
derivatives to begin changing and so you
have to smooth things out
and that's why momentum and related
methods become much more important for
stoastic gradient and mini batch more
important than in batch because you have
in addition to the derivative changing
from location to location the loss
function itself jiggles from iteration
to iteration causing the derivative to
change and so
how did we do the momentum so so the way
we're going to account for it is by
somehow
taking care of two things how we compute
the derivative
and how we update our parameters.
How did we do this in the momentum
method?
Anybody remember how did we do this in
the momentum method? Anyone?
Very easy. But how did we do this in the
momentum method?
We've already explained this. Come on
guys. Someone
running average, right? Thanks, Shir. We
maintained a running average of the
derivatives. So we said this the steps
the step is always minus
the derivative right so minus derivative
of a loss and so we maintained a running
average of these guys that was given by
this formula here the running average is
beta*
the previous running average plus some
times the current correction which is
the correction is always minus the gra
the minus the gradient. Right? So that's
why you have the minus. So does
everybody see how this is the running
average?
Yes or no?
Right? I see one. Yes. What about the
rest of you guys? Right? And so and then
we correct using the running average.
This was the momentum method and it
worked really nicely. So this was this
illustration that we had I found on the
web which shows again the gradient is
always perpendicular to this equ the uh
uh equal value locus right the level set
and so vanilla SGD vanilla gradient
descent might find these gradients and
swing around like so but then when you
begin maintaining a running average of
all gradients then the directions in
which the gradient swings get sort of
suppressed test and you get a behavior
of this kind. So this was this mana
gradient descent. What was the
improvement on this that we suggested?
Anybody? What was the improvement that
we suggested on this?
Anyone remember?
Anybody?
What was the improvement?
scaling before
faster divergence
not quite
I'll wait for five more one more guess
before I continue what was the
improvement we suggested on this
one person anybody wants to guess before
I move on nest's momentum right so what
what did ne so the momentum method at
each point. Maybe you took a current
step. This is the current step. This is
the current step. You know, the latest
correction. Then you computed the
gradient right here and took a step
against the gradient. And then to this
you added a scaled version of the
previous step to get the overall
correction. This was the momentum
method.
Nester suggested that if you change the
order things are much faster and he
proved this. So to change the order we
did some. So this was what we did. Step
one, you went against the gradient and
then you added in a scaled version of
the previous guy. Right? If I reverse
the order, I first take a scaled version
of the previous guy to maybe come here
and then take a step against the
gradient at this location which gives me
an entirely different step. And so this
was nestros method. At each point you
first the the latest correction is
some
beta times the previous correction which
is this guy
plus
the a step against the gradient
taken at the current location which is w
+
beta * delta w k minus one.
And this is the correction that you make
to get this guy. Is this formula making
sense? The new correction is this guy
which is beta * delta w from the
previous iteration plus a step against
the gradient taken at this location
which is
you know the previous estimate plus this
additional step. So did this formula
make sense to everyone?
Yes. Huh?
Right. And so and that's the correction
you make.
Any questions?
Okay. If this made sense, give me a
thumbs up. I'll move on. I'd like to see
maybe 20 thumbs ups just before I move
on.
All right. Perfect. Okay.
And so here was a very nice example
comparison of nestros with momentum.
This is from Hinton. So here momentum
would take you out here when you're
trying to get here. But nests would just
since you're going continuing the
current direction before you make your
correction, it would converge to the
optimum much faster. And so this is a
very nice visual illustration of why
Nest is better.
Now look at this. Here is your actual
uh
so this is
actually continuing that. So what ex
just continuing with previous
explanation what the momentum
method is doing is
correcting out the
smoothing out the oscillations in the
derivative. Right? So when we do
something of this kind
the derivative might swing from instant
to instant by maintaining some kind of a
running average they it's smoothing
things out and both incremental SGD and
mini batch gradients tend to have high
variance and so momentum smooths out the
variations which results in smoother and
faster convergence.
But then if I look at same thing with
nests, right? You're uh smoothing out
the
uh oscillations in the derivative except
that you're do the manner the location
at which you're computing the derivative
changes with respect to the standard
momentum. Be that as it may, let's go
back to our uh standard update rule.
This was your standard gradient descent
update rule, right?
Yes. No.
So,
yes or no, guys? Come on, that's easy.
Okay. How many different terms
do we have over here besides the W
itself? Two of them, right? We have the
gradient and we have the learning rate.
Which of these two
does the momentum method correct smooth
out?
Which of these two does it smooth out?
The momentum method fixes gives you an
improved method of picking this guy,
right? But the learning rate you're
using is still the same as before. This
has not changed.
You agree?
Yes. No.
Okay,
let's attack the second term in your
update rule. Right, the momentum method
fixes this term to reduce unstable
oscillation.
What about this term?
Now here I give you three a sequence of
three gradients, right? The first is
this guy, the second is this guy and the
third is this guy. Will the averages be
the be different in the three cases or
are they all going to be very similar?
What do you think?
Well, the averages be going to be very
very similar, right?
But then the behavior in the vertical
direction is very different in all
three, is it not?
So in terms of learning rate for the
vertical for the horizontal direction,
would you want different learning rates
in the three cases?
In terms of learning rate, would you
want different learning rates in the
three cases? What about in the vertical
direction?
What would you want?
So, where would you want the highest
learning rate and where would you want
the lowest one
in the vertical direction?
anybody?
So the highest because this is swinging
wildly. You don't want to believe the
vertical uh movements. In this case,
this is more believable, right? So in
the vertical disc direction, the
learning rate over here, you would
expect you would want it to be greater
than the learning rate out here. But
there's nothing in the current formula
which is checking for this motion,
right?
Yes or no?
There's nothing in the formula which is
correct. Checking for this motion, is
there?
Our learning rates are just given. So
how can you adjust for this? Anybody?
How would you account for how do you
determine that this guy needs a lower
learning rate than this guy?
How would you determine this?
anyone
L2
still getting close right very nice very
nice shot so
the just some uh some uh notation I'm
going to be representing the derivative
of the loss with respect to any
parameter is partial wde the squared
derivative when I say partial squared it
doesn't mean it's the second derivative
it's the square of the derivative and so
the mean squared derivative is the
running estimate of the average squared
derivative. Okay. And I'm going to
modify my update rule. If I look over
here, the total movement is much more
than over here. So in directions where
the total movement is very large,
I want to have a lower learning rate. In
directions where the total movement is
small, I want to have a higher learning
rate. Do that make sense?
Yes. No. Yes. Okay, just give me a
second. I got to open the door.
>> Just give me a second.
Okay. So,
how do we do this? We do this in this
manner. The total movement is not the
average motion, the square. The average
cancels out as we saw, right? So, we
want to look at the square.
So, we're going to look at the average
squared value of the derivative and
we're going to because we want to keep
updating it as the data comes in. We do
this using a running average. And so
uh we're going to maintain and so now we
have this this term which is the
squared
expected value of the squared movement
which is done as a running average. This
is the previous average gamma* the
previous average 1 - gamma gamma* the
current estimate the square of the
current the current estimate of the
derivative. And so the RMS value is the
square root of this guy. This plus
epsilon is just to ensure uh that we
don't have division by zero. And so the
learning rate itself is scaled by the
inverse of the RMS value of the
derivative in each direction.
Right? Is this making sense?
That's correct. So is this making sense
to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right. And so this is the famous RMS
prop. RMS prop just
it's very similar to R prop. Meaning
the if the derivative were fixed then
the RMS value and the original value
would be the same. These two would
cancel out and you' just be left with a
fixed step size. So it looks like R
prop. That's why they called it RMS prop
in the first case. But then basically
what it did was that it fixes the
learning rate to uh cancel out the
swings in
in in in directions where you have too
much movement. So toana over here if you
if you don't decrease the learning rate
in the vertical direction then you're
going to have a lot of movement over
here then a lot of movement over here a
lot of movement over here it's not going
to be very good. So when you see a lot
of movement it means that you don't
believe that movement.
That answer your question.
Yes. Now
>> yes uh but I was to the equation the
equation of the RMS prop that I didn't
get like why do you
>> so because this is the RMS value root
mean squared value right? And if you
look over here, this is going to be a
large squared value. This is going to be
a large squared value. So when you look
at the root mean squared value, that's
going to be large for this one and small
for this one.
>> Yeah, I get it now.
>> Okay, that's all. So that's why we have
this m this method, right? So
and so here's here's what we have. RMS
prop fixed this guy. Momentum methods
fixed this guy, right?
Can we do something even better?
What is the next obvious thing? Momentum
only fixes the green thing. RMS prop
only fixes the term highlighted in
yellow. Join them. Do both. Right? And
so combine them. Perfect. And so that's
what we are going to do. And that gives
us the most popular learning algorithm
of all. That's Adam. which is simply RMS
prop with momentum. As before, you're
going to maintain a running average
of the derivative
and then you're going to maintain a
running average of the
squared derivative.
And the update rule is simply going to
use the running average of the
derivative
and normalize the learning rate by the
RMS value of the derivative.
This make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Yes. Okay. Right. Very easy.
There's this extra some hacky looking
thing over here and it's uh well it's
it's actually a hack. Why? Because
typically your delta values tend to be
very small close to zero. And so what
will happen is that in the beginning uh
I mean the so uh
delta value is going to be zero actually
the delta values the way we would do it
is uh the delta values close to zero.
Yeah these things will not after the
first iteration you will find that
things don't actually change it
saturates very quickly. So this ensures
that in the early iterations
uh so the delta values actually tend to
be very close to one in your running
average because if the delta values are
close to zero then you're always
following the latest term. So this tends
to be high in to to get a good running
average. But if delta value is close to
one in the beginning this guy will
hardly have any influence at all. So
also this guy will have hardly any
influence at all. And so the algorithm
will take forever to actually get into
move motion. And so
uh we have this division by 1 / gamma ra
to k which makes sure that in the early
estimates
the uh updates are quick but then after
a little while the gamma ra to k becomes
close to zero and then this just becomes
standard running averages. So this term
over here is just a way to ensure that
that things don't get stuck early in the
iterations. But the key thing is that
you're combining a running average of
the mean and a running average of the
variance to get which which is uh
combines both the momentum and the swing
to get your update roots. Right? And
typically mu0 the initial estimate for
mu tends to be zero. Delta tends to be
close to one. And this is just an
explanation for why we have this
denominator term. There are many other
variants of this same theme. AdamW, add
a grad delta, you name it. But all of
them follow the same basic principle and
you're right, right? some minor min
minor fixes but this basic principle
that you adjust both individually just
by this very simple principle of
maintaining running averages and that
gives you a huge improvement in how
things are learned. So this is the final
poll and then after this I only have
some examples for you guys
which you may or not want to look at.
I'll give you only 30 seconds for this.
That's right, Martin. That's it. AdamW
just has been DK. We'll talk about it in
the next class.
All right, I'm ending the poll here
because we're out of time. Anybody want
to tell me which ones are the two
statements here?
What are the true statements we're out
of? So, anyone
does vanilla SG SGD
last four all of them, right? Uh
>> very SGD does not consider the long-term
trends of gradients momentum methods.
No, this should be wrong. This should be
the first one. This first statement is
wrong. from this is the the next photo
right okay uh we'll stop the class right
here but just these are some very nice
pictures that I found from uh this
chronal radford for different functions
these are showing this equal value
contours level sets the optimum is over
here and you can see how the different
methods behave and you will find that in
general momentum and nest off tend to go
off in different directions but actually
get there as fast as some of the more
adaptive methods. Here's a nice one
which shows you how things behave really
well. This is a saddle SGD just gets
stuck out here.
All the others
get to the optimum and interestingly
uh you can see that add delta is the
first fastest one but nestro accelerated
gradient gets second fastest in this
case. I think
Nestros gets there fastest. So in
general, Nestros method all by itself
tends to be as good as anything else in
the long term, but Adam is the best one
overall. Right? So to end the lesson,
the gradient descent can be sped up by
incremental updates. Convergence is
guaranteed under most conditions. Uh the
learning rates must must shrink with
time. Stoastic gradient descent update
after each observation can be much
faster than batch learning. Mini batch
updates. You update after mini batches
can be more efficient than SGD.
Convergence can be improved using smooth
updates, RMS prop
and more advanced techniques. So, did
all of this? Did the lecture make sense
to all of you guys?
Did the lecture make sense?
I'll stop the recording right here.